<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://tushar2411.github.io/networking/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://tushar2411.github.io/networking/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-01-05T07:01:25-06:00</updated><id>https://tushar2411.github.io/networking/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Computer Networking And Cybersecurity</title><subtitle>your daily dose of networks and cybersecurity articles, tutorials</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Networking Tutorial 2:- Network And Topology</title><link href="https://tushar2411.github.io/networking/releases/2021/01/04/networking-Tutorial-02.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Networking Tutorial 2:- Network And Topology" /><published>2021-01-04T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-01-04T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://tushar2411.github.io/networking/releases/2021/01/04/networking-Tutorial-02</id><author><name>Tushar Sharma</name></author><category term="releases" /><summary type="html">Networks Interconnection of set of device capable of communication. The device could be a host(computer) or a router or a modem. Network Criteria Performance: Measured in transit time and response time. Depends on users, factors, transmission time, capabilities of hardware and efficiency of software. Often evaluted by throughput and delay. If we try to send more data to the network, we may increase throughput but we increase the delay because of traffic congestion in the network. Reliability: Network reliability is inversely proportional to frequency of failure. Security: Data should be transmitted from authorized access, policies and procedures should be implemented for recovery from breaches and data loses. Physical Structure Point to point Connection: It provides a dedicated link between two devices. example: connection with controller while changing channels on t.v. Multipoint or Multidrop Connection: Connection one in which more than two specific devices share a single link. Capacity of the link is shared: If several devices use simultaneously it is spatially shared connection. If users must take turn than it is timeshared connection. example: server access by multiple people. Network Topologies It refer to the way in which a network is laid out physically. Two or more devices connect to a link. Two or more link form a topology. There are four basic types of topologies: mesh star bus ring 1. Mesh Topology Every device has a dedicated point to point link to every other device. To find number of physical links in a fully connected topology: number of links = n(n-1)/2 ; n = number of nodes or devices Advantages: Eliminates traffic problems Robust Privacy and Security Fault identification due to P2P(point to point) links Disadvantages: Amount of cabling and number of I/O ports Installation and reconnetion difficulty Expensive Space availability shortage Example: Telephone regional offices 2. Star Topology Each device has dedicated P2P connected to a controller or hub. Device not directly linked to each other. Data transmission via hub to other devices. Advantages: Less expansive Easy to install and reconfigure Less cabling Robust Disadvantages: Whole dependency on hub If hub goes down system is dead More cables required in some cases Example: used on LAN 3. Bus Topology Bus topology is a multipoint connection. One long cable acts as a backbone to link to all devices in a network. Devices are connected to the backbone using connectors. Advantages: Ease of installation Uses less cable than others Main cable travels to each device Disadvantages: Difficult reconnection and fault isolation Difficult to add new device Degradation of quality Break in bus cable causes noise in both direction Example: Ethernet’s LAN’s 4. Ring Topology Each device has a dedicated P2P connection. Connection with only the two devices on either side of it. Signal is passed in the ring in one direction until it reaches its destination. Repeater regenerates bits and passes them along. Advantages: Easy to install and configure To add a device or remove requires changing only 2 connections Fault isolation is simplified Disadvantages: Unidirectional Single break in connection disrupt entire network Less popular Example: Used in early IBM LAN network So here we end our tutorial for the networking tutorial series Please do read if you are interested in networking In next tutorial we will study about- The History of Network, The almighty Internet and Switching</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Networking Tutorial 1:- Data Communication</title><link href="https://tushar2411.github.io/networking/releases/2020/12/29/Networking-Tutorial-01.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Networking Tutorial 1:- Data Communication" /><published>2020-12-29T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-12-29T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://tushar2411.github.io/networking/releases/2020/12/29/Networking-Tutorial-01</id><author><name>Tushar Sharma</name></author><category term="releases" /><summary type="html">Data Communication Data communication is the exchange of data between two devices via some form of transmission medium such as a wire cable. Effectiveness Of Data Communication The effectiveness of the data communication depends on:- Delivery: Data must be received by intended user. Accuracy: Accurate data should be delivered to user. Timeliness: Data should be delivered in timely manner. Jitter: It refers to the variation in the packet arrival. Components OF Data Communication Message: Information(data) to be communicated. Sender: Device that sends the message. Receiver: Device that receives message. Transmission Medium: Path through which data transfers from sender to receiver. Protocol: Set of rules for the transmission. Data Communication Model Data Representation Information today comes in different forms such as text, numbers, image, audio and video. Text Text is represented in the form of bit pattern, which is a sequence of bits (0’s and 1’s). Different sets of bit pattern have been designed to represent text symbols. Each set is called code and the process of designating the symbols is called coding. Today the prevalent coding that is being used is unicode uses 32 bits to represent each symbol or character used in any language in the world. Note: ASCII or American Standard Code For Information Interchange constitutes of first 127 character of the unicode. Numbers Numbers are also represented by bit patterns. They are also represented in a ASCII table. Image Image is composed of a matrix of pixel (image elements).The size of the pixel depends on the resolution of the pixel. Each pixel is assigned a bit pattern and the bit pattern depends on the the size of the pixel. Size of the pixel of the image depends on the basis of there types. for example- black and white, greyscale, RGB and YCM. Audio Here audio refers to the recording or broadcasting of sound or music. Audios are alot different than the other form of data such as images, numbers and text. It is continuous not discrete even when we change it to an electrical signal we create a continuous signal. Video It also refers to broadcasting but of a picture or movie. It can be both continuous entity (e.g. using a camera) or a discrete entity using a number of images where each represents a discrete entity. Data Flow There are multiple methods by which data transmission takes place between devices which varies on the need and type of our devices. There are three types of data flow techniques which are used: Simplex Mode: In simplex mode, the communication is unidirectional as on a one way street. Only one device on the network can send and only one device can receive the data. Simplex mode is most commonly used in devices like keyboard and mouse. Half-Dulpex Mode: In the duplex mode both the devices on the network can behave like sender and receiver and transmit data to each other. A common example for duplex mode are walky-talkies. Full-Duplex Mode: In Full-Duplex mode both the devices can perform sender and receiver task either ways but unlike half duplex they can perform tasks simultaneously.A common example of full duplex mode is the telephone network. When two individuals are talking to each other on a telephone network they can talk and listen at same time. So that is it for our first tutorial of computer networking, In next tutorial we will learn about networks. please do share your suggestions and feedback in comments.</summary></entry></feed>